<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Beni Stocker</title>
    <link>https://stineb.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Beni Stocker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://stineb.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying drought impacts in a data-rich world</title>
      <link>https://stineb.github.io/post/soilm_global/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 11:56:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stineb.github.io/post/soilm_global/</guid>
      <description>We live in a data-rich world. Satellites are collecting information about the state of the Earth surface in ever more fine-grained resolution. CO2 and water exchange fluxes between the vegetation and the atmosphere are continuously measured at several hundred sites across the globe. And (almost) all of this data is being made easily accessible to researchers from any institution or country. This data revolution has created a playground for data analysis and a testbed for models with an unprecedented potential for addressing scientific challenges and resolving pressing questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contrasting CO2 emissions from different Holocene land-use reconstructions: Does the carbon budget add up?</title>
      <link>https://stineb.github.io/post/hololu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 20:02:29 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stineb.github.io/post/hololu/</guid>
      <description>Reliable reconstructions of past land-use change are essential to address several key challenges in understanding the role of humans in the Earth’s environmental history. Here we discuss how to integrate our understanding of past carbon cycle changes within constraints of the land carbon budget.
(This article is scheduled to be published in the PAGES Magazine Special Issue on Past Land Use and Land Cover Change)
Particular features in the ice-core CO2 and CH4 records have been hypothesized to be linked to the rise and fall of agriculture and societies (Ruddiman 2003) and have been used to serve as stratigraphic markers for the Anthropocene (Lewis and Maslin 2015).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why we need ecosystem manipulation experiments to reveal the coupled C-N system’s behaviour</title>
      <link>https://stineb.github.io/post/cn_experiments/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 13:17:30 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stineb.github.io/post/cn_experiments/</guid>
      <description>In this blog, I’m going to argue why it is crucial to use observational data from ecosystem manipulation experiments (EME) for model evaluation and calibration. And I’m going to make this case using the example of nitrogen limitation and how EMEs guided the development of Dynamic Global Vegetation Models (DGVMs) over the last one-and-a-half decades and repeatedly exposed their deficiencies. This, I hope, will convince you that there is a great future in a close relationship between modellers and experimentalists around the data from EMEs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fertility Question: How do soil nutrients influence the carbon cycle?</title>
      <link>https://stineb.github.io/post/fertilityquestion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2015 13:31:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stineb.github.io/post/fertilityquestion/</guid>
      <description>A general notion of “soil fertility” is commonly left unaccounted for in models of the terrestrial biosphere and has received relatively little attention in carbon cycle science. This changed since the presentation of results by Vicca et al. (2012) and Fernandez-Martinez et al. (2014).
Using data from forests around the globe where gross primary productivity (GPP) has been measured in parallel to changes in ecosystem biomass storage, these authors showed that forests produce biomass more efficiently on fertile soils.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Big N Question: What controls rates of nitrogen fixation and losses?</title>
      <link>https://stineb.github.io/post/nquestion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 13:35:04 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stineb.github.io/post/nquestion/</guid>
      <description>To address this question, we have to start with the notion that, on the long term, N losses from ecosystems via gaseous and leaching pathways have to be compensated by N inputs. Natural, that is non-human affected, N inputs are small and have been shown not to be sufficient to explain the measured N balance. Biological N fixation (BNF) must account for the remainder. However, drawing a complete picture of the N budget in terrestrial ecosystems has been notoriously difficult, because BNF is practically impossible to measure and estimated rates of global BNF range from around 200 TgN (Cleveland et al.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>